<indexterm significance="preferred" class="startofrange" id="npcap-indexterm"><primary>Npcap</primary></indexterm>

<sect1 id="npcap-overview">
  <title>Npcap: Nmap Project's packet sniffing library for Windows, based on WinPcap/Libpcap improved with NDIS 6 and LWF</title>

  <para>
  Npcap is an update of <ulink role="hidepdf" url="http://www.winpcap.org/">WinPcap</ulink>
  to <ulink role="hidepdf" url="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows/hardware/ff565492(v=vs.85).aspx">NDIS 6 Light-Weight Filter (LWF)</ulink> technique.
  It supports <command>Windows Vista, 7, 8 and 10</command>. It is sponsored
  by the <ulink role="hidepdf" url="http://nmap.org/">Nmap Project</ulink>
  and developed by <ulink role="hidepdf" url="http://www.veotax.com/">Yang Luo</ulink>
  under <ulink role="hidepdf" url="https://www.google-melange.com/gsoc/project/details/google/gsoc2013/hsluoyz/5727390428823552">Google Summer of Code 2013</ulink> and
  <ulink role="hidepdf" url="https://www.google-melange.com/gsoc/project/details/google/gsoc2015/hsluoyz/5723971634855936">2015</ulink>.
  It also received many helpful tests from <ulink role="hidepdf" url="https://www.wireshark.org/">Wireshark</ulink>
  and <ulink role="hidepdf" url="http://www.netscantools.com/">NetScanTools</ulink>.
  </para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="ncat-features">
  <title>Features</title>
	
  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem><para><emphasis>NDIS 6 Support</emphasis>: Npcap makes use of new LWF driver in
  Windows Vista and later (the legacy driver is used on XP). It's faster
  than the legacy <ulink role="hidepdf" url="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows/hardware/ff557012(v=vs.85).aspx">NDIS 5 Intermediate</ulink>
  technique. One reason is that
  packet data stucture has changed (from <varname>NDIS_PACKET</varname> to <varname>NET_BUFFER_LIST</varname>)
  since Vista and NDIS 5 needs to handle extra packet structure conversion.</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para><emphasis><quote>Admin-only Mode</quote> Support</emphasis>: Npcap supports to restrict its
  use to Administrators for safety purpose. If Npcap is installed with
  the option <quote>Restrict Npcap driver's access to Administrators only</quote> checked,
  when a non-Admin user tries to start a user software (Nmap, Wireshark, etc),
  the <ulink role="hidepdf" url="http://windows.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/what-is-user-account-control#1TC=windows-7">User Account Control (UAC)</ulink>
  dialog will prompt asking for Administrator privilege. Only when the end
  user chooses Yes, the driver can be accessed. This is similar to UNIX
  where you need root access to capture packets.</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para><emphasis><quote>WinPcap Compatible Mode</quote>
  Support</emphasis>: <quote>WinPcap Compatible Mode</quote> is used to decide whether Npcap should coexist With WinPcap or
  be compatible with WinPcap. With <quote>WinPcap Compatible Mode</quote> OFF, Npcap
  can coexist with WinPcap and share the DLL binary interface with WinPcap.
  So the applications unaware of Npcap <emphasis>SHOULD</emphasis> be able to use Npcap
  automatically if WinPcap is unavailable. The applications who knows
  Npcap's existence can choose to use Npcap or WinPcap first. The key
  about which is loaded first is DLL Search Path. With <quote>WinPcap Compatible Mode</quote> OFF, Npcap installs its DLLs into <filename>C:\Windows\System32\Npcap\</filename>
  instead of WinPcap's <filename>C:\Windows\System32\</filename>. So applications who want
  to load Npcap first must make <filename>C:\Windows\System32\Npcap\</filename> precedent
  to other paths in ways such as calling <function>SetDllDirectory</function>, etc. Another
  point is Npcap uses service name <quote>npcap</quote> instead of WinPcap's <quote>npf</quote> with
  <quote>WinPcap Compatible Mode</quote> OFF. So applications using <command>net start npf</command>
  for starting service must use <command>net start npcap</command> instead. If you want
  100% compatibility with WinPcap, you should install Npcap choosing
  <quote>WinPcap Compatible Mode</quote> (<quote>Install Npcap in WinPcap API-compatible Mode</quote>).
  In this mode, Npcap will install its Dlls in WinPcap's <filename>C:\Windows\System32\</filename>
  and use the <quote>npf</quote> service name. It's notable that before installing in
  this mode, you must uninstall WinPcap first (the installer wizard will
  prompt you that).</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para><emphasis>Loopback Packets Capture Support</emphasis>: Now Npcap is able to
  see Windows loopback packets using <ulink role="hidepdf" url="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows/desktop/aa366510(v=vs.85).aspx">Windows Filtering Platform (WFP)</ulink>
  technique. After installation, Npcap will create an adapter named <quote>Npcap
  Loopback Adapter</quote> for you. If you are a Wireshark user, choose this adapter
  to capture, you will see all loopback traffic the same way as other
  non-loopback adapters. Try it by typing in commands like <command>ping 127.0.0.1</command>
  (IPv4) or <command>ping ::1</command> (IPv6).</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para><emphasis>Loopback Packets Send Support</emphasis>: Besides loopback packets
  capturing, Npcap can also send out loopback packets based on
  <ulink role="hidepdf" url="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows/hardware/ff556958(v=vs.85).aspx">Winsock Kernel (WSK)</ulink>
  technique. A user software (e.g. Nmap) can just send packets
  out using <quote>Npcap Loopback Adapter</quote> like other adapters.
  <quote>Npcap Loopback Adapter</quote>
  will automatically remove the packet's Ethernet header and
  inject the payload into Windows TCP/IP stack, so this kind of loopback
  packet never go out of the machine.</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para><emphasis>Raw 802.11 Packets Capture Support</emphasis>: Npcap is able to see
  <emphasis>802.11</emphasis> packets instead of <emphasis>fake Ethernet</emphasis> packets on ordinary wireless
  adapters. You need to select the <option>Support raw 802.11 traffic (and monitor
  mode) for wireless adapters</option> option in the installation wizard to enable
  this feature. When your adapter is in <quote>Monitor Mode</quote>, Npcap will supply all
  <emphasis>802.11 data + control + management</emphasis> packets with radiotap headers. When
  your adapter is in <quote>Managed Mode</quote>, Npcap will only supply <emphasis>802.11 data</emphasis>
  packets with radiotap headers. Moreover, Npcap provides the <filename>WlanHelper.exe</filename>
  tool to help you switch to <quote>Monitor Mode</quote> on Windows. See more details
  about this feature in section <quote>For software that use Npcap raw 802.11
  feature</quote>. See more details about radiotap here:
  <ulink role="hidepdf" url="http://www.radiotap.org/">http://www.radiotap.org/</ulink></para></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="npcap-architecture">
  <title>Architecture</title>

  <para>
  Npcap tries to <emphasis>keep the original WinPcap architecture as much as possible</emphasis>.
  As the table shows, you will find it very similar with WinPcap.
  </para>
  
  <table frame='all'><title>Npcap Architecture</title>
  <tgroup cols='3' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
  <thead>
  <row>
    <entry>Binary</entry>
    <entry>Source</entry>
    <entry>Description</entry>
  </row>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
  <row>
    <entry>wpcap.dll</entry>
    <entry>wpcap</entry>
    <entry>the libpcap API, added "loopback support" to original WinPcap</entry>
  </row>
  <row>
    <entry>Packet.dll</entry>
    <entry>packetWin7\Dll</entry>
    <entry>the Packet API for Windows, added "Admin-only Mode" to original WinPcap</entry>
  </row>
  <row>
    <entry><replaceable>npf</replaceable>.sys (or <replaceable>npcap</replaceable>.sys)</entry>
    <entry>packetWin7\npf</entry>
    <entry>the driver, ported from NDIS 5 to NDIS 6, we support two names: <replaceable>npf</replaceable> or <replaceable>npcap</replaceable>, based on whether Npcap is installed in <quote>WinPcap Compatible Mode</quote></entry>
  </row>
  <row>
    <entry>NPFInstall.exe</entry>
    <entry>packetWin7\NPFInstall</entry>
    <entry>a LWF &amp; WFP driver installation tool we added to Npcap</entry>
  </row>
  <row>
    <entry>NPcapHelper.exe</entry>
    <entry>packetWin7\Helper</entry>
    <entry>the helper program for <quote>Admin-only Mode</quote>, will run under <emphasis>Administrator</emphasis> rights</entry>
  </row>
  <row>
    <entry>WlanHelper.exe</entry>
    <entry>packetWin7\WlanHelper</entry>
    <entry>a tool is used to set/get the operation mode (like <quote>Monitor Mode</quote>) for a wireless adapter, will run under <emphasis>Administrator</emphasis> rights</entry>
  </row>
  </tbody>
  </tgroup>
  </table>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="npcap-detect">
  <title>How to detect what version Npcap/WinPcap you are using?</title>
  
  <para>
  Sometimes, our user software needs to detect the existence of Npcap/WinPcap at install-time or run-time. Although Npcap's GUI installer has the ability to handle this, you may want to handle it by yourself in some conditions, like you run Npcap installer in silent-mode.
  The run-time detection is even more useful. Your software probably has some functions that rely on Npcap's particular features (like the loopback interface). You need to know if you are running on top of Npcap or the legacy WinPcap to control whether to switch your functions on.
  Fortunately, Npcap provides you some methods to detect Npcap/WinPcap at install-time and run-time.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="npcap-detect-version">
    <title>Npcap version</title>

    <para>
    You may notice that Npcap has several version strings. The installer name can be something
	like <filename>npcap-0.07-r5.exe</filename>. <quote>0.07</quote> is the version number, and
	<quote>r5</quote> is the revision number. We use a version number less than <quote>1.00</quote>
	to imply that it's still a beta release. This naming follows the Nmap's convension. However,
	WinPcap follows a different version system. It has three dotted figures like <quote>4.1.3</quote>,
	which is more Wireshark-like. One thing you need to know here is that Npcap starts the
	development based on the latest WinPcap <quote>4.1.3</quote>. So any Npcap release is more
	<emphasis>advanced</emphasis> than WinPcap's latest release. Another thing needs to notice is
	that, the <quote>0.07</quote> version number can be obtained from the
	<function>pcap_lib_version</function> function. The <quote>r5</quote> revision number
	<emphasis>only</emphasis> appears in the installer filename, it doesn't show its existence
	in any code or functions. So you'd better not determine anything based on Npcap revision
	number. Just use the latest release.
    </para>

    <para>
    The executable file version (aka e-version in this document) is another thing we need to notice.
	A e-version has four dotted figures on Windows. Npcap's e-version is something like
	<quote>5.0.7.424</quote>. <quote>5</quote> here is used to advance Npcap version than the legacy
	WinPcap's e-version <quote>4.1.0.2980</quote> because <quote>5.0.7.424</quote> is larger than
	<quote>4.1.0.2980</quote>. The legacy WinPcap installer and Wireshark uses e-version to check
	the version of WinPcap. Usually these legacy codes don't even know Npcap. So Npcap needs to
	make them simply think Npcap is a newer version of WinPcap. <quote>0</quote> and <quote>7</quote>
	in Npcap's e-version corresponds to Npcap's version <quote>0.07</quote>. <quote>424</quote> means
	that this release is built at date <quote>4.24</quote> (aka 24th, April). When Npcap version jumps
	to a new version (like from <quote>0.06</quote> to <quote>0.07</quote>), the e-version will also
	change (like from <quote>0.6.0.301</quote> to <quote>0.7.0.424</quote>). A revision update won't
	cause a change of version or e-version.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="npcap-detect-install-time">
    <title>Install-time detection</title>

    <para>
    You can check the existence of <filename>C:\Program Files\Npcap\NPFInstall.exe</filename> to
	detect Npcap's existence. If Npcap exists, you can check the file version of
	<filename>C:\Program Files\Npcap\NPFInstall.exe</filename> to detect Npcap e-version. The
	e-version also gives you the version. The NSIS code is shown below. <varname>$inst_ver</varname>
	is an e-version string like <quote>5.0.7.424</quote>
    </para>
<screen>
GetDllVersion "C:\Program Files\Npcap\NPFInstall.exe" $R0 $R1
IntOp $R2 $R0 / 0x00010000
IntOp $R3 $R0 &amp; 0x0000FFFF
IntOp $R4 $R1 / 0x00010000
IntOp $R5 $R1 &amp; 0x0000FFFF
StrCpy $inst_ver "$R2.$R3.$R4.$R5"
</screen>

    <para>
    You can check the installation options of an already installed Npcap by reading the registry
	key: <filename>HKEY_LOCAL_MACHINE\SYSTEM\CurrentControlSet\Services\npf</filename>
	(WinPcap compatible mode) or <filename>HKEY_LOCAL_MACHINE\SYSTEM\CurrentControlSet\Services\npcap</filename>
	(Non-WinPcap compatible mode). the entries like <filename>AdminOnly</filename>,
	<filename>Loopback</filename>, <filename>DltNull</filename>,<filename>Dot11Support</filename>,
	<filename>VlanSupport</filename>, <filename>WinPcapCompatible</filename>, etc. show the installation options.
	<filename>Loopback</filename> is <code>REG_SZ</code> type. A non-NULL value indicates the option is
	<emphasis>CHECKED</emphasis>. All other entries are <code>REG_DWORD</code> type. A 0x00000001 value
	indicates the option is <emphasis>CHECKED</emphasis>.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="npcap-detect-run-time">
    <title>Run-time detection</title>

    <para>
    Npcap and WinPcap can be installed together on a symtem. Which capture library is used by the
	user software relies on the DLL loading path. If Npcap's <filename>wpcap.dll</filename> is loaded first, then you
	are using Npcap, vice versa. However, it's difficult and fragile to check the DLL loading path by yourself.
	So we provide a better way: Npcap exports a <function>pcap_get_servicename</function> function in its libpcap
	API. It returns the string of Npcap service name (aka <replaceable>%SERVICE_NAME%</replaceable>), which can be used to start the service using
	<command>net start <replaceable>%SERVICE_NAME%</replaceable></command> command.
	<replaceable>%SERVICE_NAME%</replaceable> is <varname>NPF</varname> if Npcap is installed
	in <quote>WinPcap Compatible Mode</quote> and <varname>NPCAP</varname> if Npcap is installed
	at <quote>Non-WinPcap Compatible Mode</quote> (Notice: the returned string is upper-case, and
	you don't need to free its memory). You need to dynamically import this function if you want
	to call it because WinPcap doesn't have this function and it's obviously not in the WinPcap
	SDK. The C code of the <function>pcap_get_servicename</function> usage is shown below.
    </para>
<screen>
typedef char* (__cdecl *MY_PCAP_GET_SERVICENAME) ();

HINSTANCE hinstLib;
// Get a handle to the wpcap DLL module.
hinstLib = LoadLibrary(TEXT("wpcap.dll"));
MY_PCAP_GET_SERVICENAME pcap_get_servicename;
char *servicename_buf;

// If the handle is valid, try to get the function address.  
if (hinstLib != NULL)
{
	pcap_get_servicename = (MY_PCAP_GET_SERVICENAME)GetProcAddress(hinstLib, "pcap_get_servicename");
	// If the function address is valid, call the function.  

	if (pcap_get_servicename != NULL)
	{
		printf("Notice: You are using Npcap.\n");
		servicename_buf = pcap_get_servicename();
		// servicename_buf = "NPF" or "NPCAP"
		printf("Npcap service name: %s\n", servicename_buf);
	}
	else
	{
		printf("Notice: You are using WinPcap.\n");
	}

	// Free the DLL module.  
	FreeLibrary(hinstLib);
}
else
{
	printf("Notice: Neither Npcap nor WinPcap is installed.\n");
}
</screen>
  </sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="npcap-feature-native">
  <title>For software that use Npcap native mode</title>
  
  <para>
  Prerequisite: Uncheck the <option>Install Npcap in WinPcap API-compatible Mode</option> option at install-time.
  </para>
  
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>Npcap installs its DLLs into <filename>C:\Windows\System32\Npcap\</filename>
    instead of WinPcap's <filename>C:\Windows\System32\</filename>. So applications who want
    to load Npcap first must make <filename>C:\Windows\System32\Npcap\</filename> precedent
    to other paths in ways such as calling <function>SetDllDirectory</function>, etc.</para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>Npcap uses service name <quote>npcap</quote> instead of WinPcap's <quote>npf</quote> with
    <quote>WinPcap Compatible Mode</quote> OFF. So applications using <command>net start npf</command>
    for starting service must use <command>net start npcap</command> instead. The service name
    can be obtained using the <function>pcap_get_servicename</function> function. See section
    <quote>Run-time detection</quote> for the usage of <function>pcap_get_servicename</function>.</para></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="npcap-feature-loopback">
  <title>For software that use Npcap loopback feature</title>

  <para>
  Prerequisite: Check the <option>Support loopback traffic ("Npcap Loopback Adapter" will be created)</option> option at install-time.
  </para>

  <para>
  Npcap's loopback adapter device is based on <quote>Microsoft KM-TEST Loopback Adapter</quote>
  (Win8 and Win10) or <quote>Microsoft Loopback Adapter</quote> (Vista, Win7). It is an Ethernet
  adapter, and Npcap has changed its behavior and rename it to <quote>Npcap Loopback Adapter</quote>,
  to make it see the real loopback traffic only. The traffic captured by original WinPcap will not appear here.
  </para>

  <para>
  The IP address of <quote>Npcap Loopback Adapter</quote> is usually like 169.254.x.x. However,
  this IP is totally meaningless. Software using Npcap should regard this interface's IP address
  as 127.0.0.1 (IPv4) and ::1 (IPv6). This work can't be done by Npcap because Windows forbids
  any IP address to be configured as 127.0.0.1 or ::1 as they're reserved.
  </para>

  <para>
  The MAC address of <quote>Npcap Loopback Adapter</quote> is usually like 02:00:4C:4F:4F:50. However,
  this address is meaningless too. Software using Npcap should think this interface doesn't own a
  MAC address, as the loopback traffic never goes to link layer. For software using Npcap to
  capture loopback traffic, the MAC addresses in captured data will be all zeros (aka 00:00:00:00:00:00).
  For software using Npcap to send loopback traffic, any MAC addresses can be specified as they
  will be ignored. But notice that ether_type in Ethernet header should be set correctly. Only <option>IPv4</option>
  and <option>IPv6</option> are accepted. Other values like <option>ARP</option> will be ignored. (You don't need an ARP request for
  loopback interface)
  </para>

  <para>
  The MTU of <quote>Npcap Loopback Adapter</quote> is hard-coded to 65536 by Npcap. Software
  using Npcap should get this value automatically and no special handling is needed. This value is
  determined personally by me and doesn't mean Windows loopback stack can only support packet size
  as large as 65536. So don't feel weird if you have captured packets whose size are larger than it.
  </para>

  <para>
  Don't try to make OID requests to <quote>Npcap Loopback Adapter</quote> except
  <varname>OID_GEN_MAXIMUM_TOTAL_SIZE</varname> (MTU). Those requests will still succeed like
  other adapters do, but they only make sense for NDIS adapters and Npcap doesn't even use the
  NDIS way to handle the loopback traffic. The only handled OID request by Npcap is
  <varname>OID_GEN_MAXIMUM_TOTAL_SIZE</varname>. If you query its value, you will always get
  65550 (65536 + 14). If you try to set its value, the operation will always fail.
  </para>

  <para>
  To conclude, a software that wants to support Npcap loopback feature should do these steps:
  </para>
  
  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem><para>Detect Npcap Loopback Adapter's presence, by reading registry value Loopback
  at key <filename>HKEY_LOCAL_MACHINE\SYSTEM\CurrentControlSet\Services\<replaceable>npf</replaceable></filename>
  (or <replaceable>npcap</replaceable> if you installed Npcap With <quote>WinPcap Compatible Mode</quote>
  OFF). If <filename>Loopback value</filename> exsits, it means <quote>Npcap Loopback Adapter</quote> is OK.
  Then perform the following steps.</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>Treat the IP address of <quote>Npcap Loopback Adapter</quote> as 127.0.0.1 (IPv4) and ::1 (IPv6).</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>Treat the MAC address of <quote>Npcap Loopback Adapter</quote> as 00:00:00:00:00:00.</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>If you use IP Helper API to get adapter list, you will get an interface named
  like <quote>Loopback Pseudo-Interface 1</quote>. This interface is a DUMMY interface by Microsoft
  and can't be seen in NDIS layer. And it also takes the 127.0.0.1/::1 IP address. A good practice
  for software is merging the entry of <quote>Npcap Loopback Adapter</quote> and the entry of
  <quote>Loopback Pseudo-Interface 1</quote> into one entry, like what I have implemented for Nmap (see the
  <quote>Other code (for developers)</quote> part).</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>Don't make use of OID requests for <quote>Npcap Loopback Adapter</quote>
  except <varname>OID_GEN_MAXIMUM_TOTAL_SIZE</varname> requests.</para></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="npcap-feature-dot11">
  <title>For software that use Npcap raw 802.11 feature</title>
  
  <para>
  Prerequisite: Check the <option>Support raw 802.11 traffic (and monitor mode) for wireless adapters</option> option at install-time.
  </para>
  
  <sect2 id="npcap-feature-dot11-steps">
    <title>Steps</title>
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>Install the latest version Npcap with the
	<option>Support raw 802.11 traffic (and monitor mode) for wireless adapters</option> option
	checked in the installation wizard. With this option checked, Npcap will see packets with
	<emphasis>Radiotap + 802.11</emphasis> headers for wireless adapters. Otherwise, Npcap
	will see packets with <emphasis>fake Ethernet</emphasis> headers for wireless adapters.</para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>Run <filename>WlanHelper.exe</filename> with <emphasis>Administrator privilege</emphasis>. Type in
	the index of your wireless adapter (usually <keycap>Enter</keycap>) and press <keycap>Enter</keycap>.
	Then type in <keycap>Enter</keycap> and press <keycap>Enter</keycap> to switch on the <quote>Monitor Mode</quote>.
	<filename>WlanHelper.exe</filename> also supports parameters to be used in an API manner, run
	<command>WlanHelper.exe -h</command> for details.</para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>An example: launch Wireshark and capture on the wireless adapter, you will
	see all 802.11 packets (<emphasis>data + control + management</emphasis>). Here you should
	make your software interact with Npcap using the WinPcap API (open the adapter, read packets,
	send packets, etc).</para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>If you need to return to <quote>Managed Mode</quote>, run <command>WlanHelper.exe</command>
	again and input the index of the adapter, then type in <keycap>Enter</keycap> and press
	<keycap>Enter</keycap> to switch off the <quote>Monitor Mode</quote>.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="npcap-feature-dot11-tips">
    <title>Tips</title>
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>You need to use <filename>WlanHelper.exe</filename> tool to switch on
	the <quote>Monitor Mode</quote> in order to see <emphasis>802.11 control and management</emphasis>
	packets in Wireshark (also <emphasis>encrypted 802.11 data</emphasis> packets, you need
	to specify the decipher key in Wireshark in order to decrypt those packets), otherwise you will
	only see 802.11 data packets.</para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>Switching on the <quote>Monitor Mode</quote> will disconnect your wireless
	network from the AP, you can switch back to <quote>Managed Mode</quote> using the same
	<filename>WlanHelper.exe</filename> tool.</para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>The <filename>WlanHelper.exe</filename> tool automatically installed to your
	system path after installing Npcap.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="npcap-feature-dot11-terminology">
    <title>Terminology</title>
    <para>
      <quote>Managed Mode</quote> (for Linux) = <quote>Extensible Station Mode</quote> (aka <quote>ExtSTA</quote>, for Windows)
    </para>

    <para>
      <quote>Monitor Mode</quote> (for Linux) = <quote>Network Monitor Mode</quote> (aka <quote>NetMon</quote>, for Windows)
    </para>

    <para>
      <quote>Master Mode</quote> (for Linux) = <quote>Extensible Access Point</quote> (aka <quote>ExtAP</quote>, for Windows)
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="npcap-feature-dot11-wlanhelper">
    <title>WlanHelper</title>
    <para>
      WlanHelper is used to set/get the operation mode (like <quote>Monitor Mode</quote>) for a wireless adapter on Windows.
	  WlanHelper tries to follow the grammar of <filename>iwconfig</filename>, a wireless management tool
	  for Linux. So if you rename <filename>WlanHelper.exe</filename> to <filename>iwconfig.exe</filename>,
	  your command lines for WlanHelper will be exactly the same with the iwconfig tool.
    </para>
	
    <sect3 id="npcap-feature-dot11-wlanhelper-usage">
      <title>WlanHelper's Usage</title>
      <para>
        Note: <command>WlanHelper</command> must run under <emphasis>Administrator privilege</emphasis>.
      </para>

      <sect4 id="npcap-feature-dot11-wlanhelper-usage-interactive">
        <title>Interactive way</title>
        <para>
          Run <command>WlanHelper</command> without parameters.
        </para>
      </sect4>

      <sect4 id="npcap-feature-dot11-wlanhelper-usage-api">
        <title>Command-line API way</title>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><para>Run <command>netsh wlan show interfaces</command>, get the <option>Name</option> or <option>GUID</option> for the interface.</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>Run <command>WlanHelper -h</command> to see the man page.</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <example id="npcap-ex-wlanhelper-man">
        <title>WlanHelper Man</title>
        <screen>
C:\> <userinput>WlanHelper.exe</userinput>
WlanHelper for Npcap 0.07 (http://npcap.org)
Usage: WlanHelper {Interface Name or GUID} [Options]
Options:
  mode: get interface operation mode
  mode &lt;managed|monitor|master|wfd_device|wfd_owner|wfd_client&gt;: set interface operation mode
  modes: get all operation modes supported by the interface, comma-separated
  channel: get interface channel
  channel &lt;1-11&gt;: set interface channel (only works at monitor mode)
  freq: get interface frequency
  freq &lt;0-200&gt;: set interface frequency (only works at monitor mode)
Operation Modes:
  managed - the Extensible Station (ExtSTA) operation mode
  monitor - the Network Monitor (NetMon) operation mode
  master - the Extensible Access Point (ExtAP) operation mode (supported for Windows 7 and later)
  wfd_device - the Wi-Fi Direct Device operation mode (supported for Windows 8 and later)
  wfd_owner - the Wi-Fi Direct Group Owner operation mode (supported for Windows 8 and later)
  wfd_client - the Wi-Fi Direct Client operation mode (supported for Windows 8 and later)
Examples:
  WlanHelper wi-fi mode
  WlanHelper 42dfd47a-2764-43ac-b58e-3df569c447da channel 11
  WlanHelper 42dfd47a-2764-43ac-b58e-3df569c447da freq 2
See the MAN Page (https://github.com/nmap/npcap) for more options and examples
        </screen>
        </example>
        <para>
          An example:
        </para>
        <example id="npcap-ex-wlanhelper-api">
        <title>WlanHelper API Usage</title>
        <screen>
C:\> <userinput>netsh wlan show interfaces</userinput>

There is 1 interface on the system:

    Name                   : <replaceable>Wi-Fi</replaceable>
    Description            : Qualcomm Atheros AR9485WB-EG Wireless Network Adapter
    GUID                   : <replaceable>42dfd47a-2764-43ac-b58e-3df569c447da</replaceable>
    Physical address       : a4:db:30:d9:3a:9a
    State                  : connected
    SSID                   : LUO-PC_Network
    BSSID                  : d8:15:0d:72:8c:18
    Network type           : Infrastructure
    Radio type             : 802.11n
    Authentication         : WPA2-Personal
    Cipher                 : CCMP
    Connection mode        : Auto Connect
    Channel                : 1
    Receive rate (Mbps)    : 150
    Transmit rate (Mbps)   : 150
    Signal                 : 100%
    Profile                : LUO-PC_Network

    Hosted network status  : Not available

C:\> <userinput>WlanHelper.exe <replaceable>wi-fi</replaceable> mode</userinput>
managed
C:\> <userinput>WlanHelper.exe <replaceable>wi-fi</replaceable> mode monitor</userinput>
Success
C:\> <userinput>WlanHelper.exe <replaceable>wi-fi</replaceable> mode </userinput>
monitor
C:\> <userinput>WlanHelper.exe <replaceable>wi-fi</replaceable> mode managed</userinput>
Success
C:\> <userinput>WlanHelper.exe <replaceable>wi-fi</replaceable> mode</userinput>
managed
        </screen>
        </example>
      </sect4>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="npcap-build">
  <title>Build</title>

  <para>
  Run <command>installer\Build.bat</command>: build all DLLs and the driver. The DLLs need to be built using Visual Studio 2013. And the driver needs to be built using Visual Studio 2015 with Windows SDK 10 10586 &amp; Windows Driver Kit 10 10586.
  </para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="npcap-packaging">
  <title>Packaging</title>

  <para>
  Run <command>installer\Deploy.bat</command>: copy the files from build directories to
  deployment directories and sign the files. Generate an installer named
  <filename>npcap-nmap-%VERSION%.exe</filename> using
  <ulink role="hidepdf" url="http://nsis.sourceforge.net/Special_Builds">NSIS large strings build</ulink>
  with the <ulink role="hidepdf" url="https://github.com/hsluoyz/SysRestore">SysRestore plug-in (special build for Npcap)</ulink>
  and sign the installer.
  </para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="npcap-symbols">
  <title>Generating debug symbols (optional)</title>

  <para>
  Run <command>installer\Deploy_Symbols.bat</command>: copy the debug symbol files (.PDB)
  from build directories to deployment directories and package them into a zip file named
  <filename>npcap-nmap-&lt;VERSION&gt;-DebugSymbols.zip</filename> using
  <ulink role="hidepdf" url="http://www.7-zip.org/">7-Zip</ulink>.
  </para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="npcap-redistribution">
  <title>Redistribution</title>

  <para>
  (You need to first notice our <ulink role="hidepdf" url="http://www.npcap.org/">LICENSE</ulink> before distributing Npcap)
  </para>

  <para>
  The Npcap installer is friendly for redistribution by supporting two installation
  ways: <quote>GUI Mode</quote> (direct run) and <quote>Silent Mode</quote> (run with
  <option>/s</option> paramter).
  </para>

  <sect2 id="npcap-redistribution-options">
    <title>Installation options</title>
    <para>
    The current Npcap installation options by default are (for both <quote>GUI Mode</quote> and <quote>Silent Mode</quote>):
    </para>

    <para>
    <option>/admin_only=no /loopback_support=yes /dlt_null=no /dot11_support=no /vlan_support=no /winpcap_mode=no</option>
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para><option>/admin_only=yes</option>: Restrict Npcap driver's access to Administrators only</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><option>/loopback_support=yes</option>: Support loopback traffic (<quote>Npcap Loopback Adapter</quote> will be created)</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><option>/dlt_null=yes</option>: Use <varname>DLT_NULL</varname> as the loopback interface' link layer protocol instead of <varname>DLT_EN10MB</varname></para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><option>/dot11_support=yes</option>: Support raw 802.11 traffic (and <quote>Monitor Mode</quote>) for wireless adapters</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><option>/vlan_support=yes</option>: Support 802.1Q VLAN tag when capturing and sending data</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><option>/winpcap_mode=yes</option>: Install Npcap in WinPcap API-compatible Mode</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="npcap-redistribution-options-gui">
    <title>How to change default options for GUI Mode installation</title>
    <para>
    Default options for Npcap installer GUI can be changed. An example is:
    </para>

    <para>
    <command>npcap-nmap-<replaceable>0.07</replaceable>.exe /admin_only=no /loopback_support=yes /dlt_null=no /dot11_support=no /vlan_support=no /winpcap_mode=yes</command>
    </para>

    <para>
    or even simpler:
    </para>

    <para>
    <command>npcap-nmap-<replaceable>0.07</replaceable>.exe /winpcap_mode=yes</command>
    </para>

    <para>
    As the default option of <option>/winpcap_mode</option> is no. Running the installer
	directly without options will see <option>Install Npcap in WinPcap API-compatible Mode</option>
	<emphasis>UNCHECKED</emphasis> by default in the <quote>Installation Options</quote> page.
	However, the above two commands will launch the installer GUI, and in the <quote>Installation Options</quote> page, the
	<option>Install Npcap in WinPcap API-compatible Mode</option> option will be <emphasis>CHECKED</emphasis> by default.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="npcap-redistribution-options-silent">
    <title>How to change options for Silent Mode installation</title>
    <para>
    An example of changing option feature for silent installation is:
    </para>

    <para>
    <command>npcap-nmap-<replaceable>0.07</replaceable>.exe /S /admin_only=no /loopback_support=yes /dlt_null=no /dot11_support=no /vlan_support=no /winpcap_mode=yes</command>
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>If you doesn't specify a paramter key, it will take the default value.
    This is the same with the GUI.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>The keys are <emphasis>case-insensitive</emphasis>.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>The values are <emphasis>case-sensitive</emphasis>, only two values are
    permitted: <option>yes</option> or <option>no</option>.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="npcap-download">
  <title>Downloads</title>

  <para>
  Latest Npcap installer: <ulink role="hidepdf" url="https://github.com/nmap/npcap/releases">Npcap Release</ulink>
  </para>

  <para>
  Archived Npcap installers (prior to <option>0.05</option>):
  <ulink role="hidepdf" url="https://svn.nmap.org/nmap-exp/yang/NPcap-LWF/npcap_history_versions/">Npcap Release (Archieve)</ulink>
  </para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="npcap-development">
  <title>Development</title>

  <sect2 id="npcap-sdk">
    <title>SDK</title>

    <para>
    Npcap has its own SDK for <quote>Non-WinPcap Compatible Mode</quote>.
    By using it, your software will run under <quote>Non-WinPcap Compatible Mode</quote>.
    We don't update the SDK as frequently as the binaries. The latest SDK is <ulink role="hidepdf" url="https://github.com/nmap/npcap/releases/tag/v0.07-r9">Npcap SDK 0.07 r9</ulink>.
    </para>

    <para>
    If you only want to build your software under <quote>WinPcap Compatible Mode</quote>
    (which is <emphasis>NOT</emphasis> recommended), please use the legacy
    <ulink role="hidepdf" url="http://www.winpcap.org/devel.htm">WinPcap 4.1.2 Developer's Pack</ulink> instead.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="npcap-documentation">
    <title>Documentation</title>

    <para>
    This document currently only addresses the Npcap particular features. It doesn't
	show you the basics about the general WinPcap usage. As Npcap shares the libpcap
	API with WinPcap, you can always refer to the
	<ulink role="hidepdf" url="https://www.winpcap.org/docs/default.htm">WinPcap documentation</ulink>
	for general usage of Npcap.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="npcap-examples">
    <title>Examples</title>

    <para>
    You can refer to <ulink role="hidepdf" url="https://github.com/nmap/npcap/tree/master/Examples">WinPcap's examples</ulink> to see the usage.
    </para>

    <para>
    I also provided an example:
	<ulink role="hidepdf" url="https://github.com/hsluoyz/UserBridge/">UserBridge</ulink>,
	which is a tool to redirect all packets from an interface to another.
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="npcap-incompatible">
  <title>The list of incompatible software</title>

  <para>
  The LWF technique Npcap used is usually a cause of conflicts between the programs
  using network drivers. The incompatible result can be <emphasis>bluescreen, no adapters,
  no traffic</emphasis>, etc. The reason can <emphasis>either be Npcap's bug or the incompatible
  software's bug</emphasis>. If the latter is the case, there's nothing much can be done by
  Npcap but for youself to remove the incompatible software.
  </para>

  <para>
  The commonly seen sources of the incompatble software are <emphasis>anti-virus,
  network firewall, VPN, traffic capture</emphasis>, etc. To help you identify those
  software, We have collected the programs that have trouble with Npcap
  according to user's report, so what you need to do is to remove them if
  your Npcap doesn't work normally.
  </para>
  
  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem><para>Avaya Collaboration Services</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Avaya Collaboration Services x64</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Avaya UCA Type Library</para></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="npcap-qa">
  <title>Q &amp; A</title>

  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem><para>Network disconnects after installing Npcap: As Microsoft states
  <ulink role="hidepdf" url="https://support.microsoft.com/en-us/kb/2019184">here</ulink>,
  <emphasis>an optional NDIS light-weight filter (LWF) driver like Npcap could cause
  90-second delay in network availability</emphasis>. Some solutions you could try
  are: 1) wait for 90 seconds; 2) disable and re-enable the adapter icon in
  <command>ncpa.cpl</command>; 3) reboot. If this doesn't help you, you should
  consider that you have <emphasis>installed some incompatible software</emphasis>.
  It can be a <emphasis>VPN, anti-virus, firewall or other network related</emphasis>
  software. We are maintaining an incompatible software list in the previous section.
  So you can uninstall all those potential software one by one, and see which one
  exactly causes the issue. Don't forget to report it to me, so I could add it to
  this list.</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Installation fails with error code <varname>0x8004a029</varname>:
  The cause is that you have <quote>reached the maximum number of network filter
  drivers</quote>, see solution
  <ulink role="hidepdf" url="https://social.technet.microsoft.com/Forums/windows/en-US/4deb27fc-33ce-4fc0-a26f-3fec5b57733d/is-there-a-maximum-number-of-network-filter-drivers-in-windows-7?forum=w7itpronetworking">here</ulink>.
  </para></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="npcap-license">
  <title>License</title>

  <para>
  See: <ulink role="hidepdf" url="https://github.com/nmap/npcap/blob/master/LICENSE">LICENSE</ulink>
  </para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="npcap-issues">
  <title>Bug report</title>

  <para>
  Please report any bugs or issues about Npcap at: <ulink role="hidepdf" url="https://github.com/nmap/nmap/issues">GitHub Issues</ulink>
  </para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="npcap-list">
  <title>Contact</title>

  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem><para><ulink role="hidepdf" url="mailto:dev@nmap.org">dev@nmap.org</ulink> (Nmap development list, this is <emphasis>preferred</emphasis>)</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para><ulink role="hidepdf" url="mailto:hsluoyz@gmail.com">hsluoyz@gmail.com</ulink> (Yang Luo's email, if your issue needs to be kept private, please contact me via this mail)</para></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</sect1>

